<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
 schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="nelson">
    
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Oscar Wilde to Major J.O. Nelson, Berneval-sur-Mer, May 1897</title> <!-- Formal title of this TEI document -->
                <author>Oscar Wilde</author>
                <respStmt> <!-- Information about responsibility for the TEI file -->
                    <resp>TEI encoding</resp> <!-- Nature of responsibility -->
                    <name>Clara Martin</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt> <!-- How the TEI file itself is published or made available -->
                <publisher>École nationale des chartes</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>
                        TEI encoding © 2025 by Clara Martin. 
                        Manuscript: The New York Public Library, Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature, 
                        Berg Coll MSS Wilde [Text]. 
                        The copyright status of the manuscript is uncertain; this encoding is provided for teaching and research use 
                        in accordance with NYPL guidance on reuse.
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc> <!-- Describes the physical manuscript as a whole, including origin, layout, and history. -->
                    <msIdentifier> <!-- Provides the archival identity of the manuscript: repository, collection, shelfmark. -->
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <settlement>New York</settlement>
                        <repository>The New York Public Library</repository>
                        <collection>Oscar Wilde collection of papers</collection>
                        <idno>Berg Coll MSS Wilde</idno> <!-- Shelf locator from the NYPL catalogue -->
                    </msIdentifier>
                    
                    <msContents> <!-- Summarizes the intellectual contents of the manuscript (what text(s) it contains). -->
                        <msItem> <!-- Describes a single textual item or work contained in the manuscript. -->
                            <title>Letter to Major J.O. Nelson</title>
                            <author>Oscar Wilde</author>
                            <note>
                                Autograph letter to <persName ref="#pers_nelson">Major J.O. Nelson</persName>, governor of 
                                <placeName ref="#place_reading_gaol">Reading Gaol</placeName>, expressing gratitude for his kindness in prison and
                                reflecting on suffering, prison life, and the possibility of reforming the system.
                            </note>
                            <textLang mainLang="en">English</textLang>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    
                    <physDesc> <!-- Physical description of the manuscript: support, layout, and hands. -->
                        <objectDesc form="letter">
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <p>
                                        Autograph letter written in ink on paper, comprising four leaves, headed 
                                        “Hotel de la Plage, Berneval-sur-Mer, Près de Dieppe”.
                                    </p>
                                </support>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout>
                                    <p>Single column of prose; line breaks preserved in this transcription.</p>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        
                        <!-- Handwriting description -->
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote scope="major">
                                <p>Autograph hand of Oscar Wilde.</p>
                            </handNote>
                            <handNote scope="minor">
                                <p>Modern archival annotations and identifiers in another hand (repository marks, order numbers).</p>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <p>
                                Written at <placeName ref="#place_berneval">Berneval-sur-Mer</placeName> on 
                                <date when="1897-05-28">28 May 1897</date>, after Wilde’s release from 
                                <placeName ref="#place_reading_gaol">Reading Gaol</placeName>, and addressed to 
                                <persName ref="#pers_nelson">Major J.O. Nelson</persName>, governor of the prison.
                            </p>
                        </origin>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
                
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl_warder_martin">
                        <title type="work" rend="italic">
                            The Case of Warder Martin: Some Cruelties of Prison Life
                        </title>
                        <author ref="#pers_wilde">Oscar Wilde</author>
                        <date when="1896">1896</date>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <note>
                            <title type="work" rend="italic">The Case of Warder Martin: Some Cruelties of Prison Life</title> 
                            is a pamphlet first published anonymously in London in 1896 and later reissued 
                            under the expanded title 
                            <title type="work" rend="italic">Children in Prison and Other Cruelties of Prison Life</title>. 
                            Although the 1896 printing was anonymous, the themes and arguments closely anticipate 
                            those expressed by <persName ref="#pers_wilde">Oscar Wilde</persName> in his public letter 
                            to the editor of <title type="periodical" rend="italic">The Daily Chronicle</title> 
                            (France, 27 May 1897), where he discussed “the Martin case” as evidence of a system 
                            in need of urgent reform. This pamphlet denounces the mistreatment of child prisoners at 
                            <placeName ref="#place_reading_gaol">Reading Gaol</placeName>, particularly the conduct of 
                            Warder Henry Isaac Martin, and offers essential contextual material for understanding 
                            Wilde’s reflections on prison life.
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc> <!-- Editorial and encoding decisions behind the TEI file. -->
            <projectDesc> <!-- Purpose, scope, and institutional context of the TEI encoding project. -->
                <p>
                    This TEI file is part of a corpus of three letters by Oscar Wilde encoded
                    for the course “Modelling Humanities Data with TEI-XML” at the École
                    nationale des chartes.
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl> <!-- Editorial principles followed during transcription. -->
                <p>
                    Diplomatic transcription following original spelling, punctuation, and
                    lineation. No normalisation has been applied; obvious abbreviations
                    (such as “Mons.”) are encoded with &lt;choice&gt;, &lt;abbr&gt;, and &lt;expan&gt;.
                </p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    
                    <person xml:id="pers_wilde">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Oscar</forename>
                            <addName type="middleName">Fingal O’Flahertie Wills</addName>
                            <surname>Wilde</surname>
                            <addName type="alias">Sebastian Melmoth</addName>
                        </persName>
                        
                        <idno type="wikidata">Q30875</idno>
                        <idno type="viaf">34464414</idno>
                        
                        <state type="occupation">
                            <p>Author, playwright, journalist, and poet associated with the Aesthetic and Decadent movements.</p>
                        </state>
                        
                        <note>
                            Oscar Fingal O’Flahertie Wills Wilde (1854–1900) was an Irish playwright, novelist, essayist, 
                            and one of the central figures of the Aesthetic movement in late Victorian Britain.  
                            Celebrated in the 1890s for his sharp wit, public persona, and comedies of manners 
                            such as <title type="work" rend="italic">The Importance of Being Earnest</title>, 
                            he fell spectacularly after his conviction for “gross indecency” in 1895.  
                            Sentenced to two years’ hard labour, Wilde was imprisoned in several institutions, 
                            including <placeName ref="#place_reading_gaol">Reading Gaol</placeName>, where he endured 
                            harsh conditions that profoundly marked his later writings.
                            
                            After his release in 1897, he adopted the alias 
                            <addName type="alias">Sebastian Melmoth</addName> during his exile in France, 
                            where he lived in poverty but remained intellectually active.  
                            His prison experience produced 
                            <title type="work" rend="italic">De Profundis</title>, a long epistolary meditation, 
                            and later inspired <title type="work" rend="italic">The Ballad of Reading Gaol</title> (1898).  
                            Wilde’s posthumous reputation has grown considerably, and he is now regarded as one of the 
                            most distinctive voices of nineteenth-century literature, noted for his stylistic brilliance, 
                            social satire, and exploration of individuality, morality, and desire.
                        </note>
                    </person>
                                        
                    <person xml:id="pers_nelson">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>James</forename>
                            <addName type="middleName">O.</addName>
                            <surname>Nelson</surname>
                            <addName type="title">Major</addName>
                        </persName>
                        
                        <state type="occupation">
                            <p>Prison governor in the British penal system, serving as Governor of Reading Gaol from 1896.</p>
                        </state>
                                                
                        <state type="relationship">
                            <p>Known for his humane treatment of Oscar Wilde during Wilde’s imprisonment in Reading Gaol.</p>
                        </state>
                        
                        <note>
                            Major James O. Nelson served as Governor of Reading Gaol from 1896. He is 
                            remembered for his exceptional humanity toward Oscar Wilde during the latter’s 
                            incarceration (1895–1897). 
                            Nelson discreetly granted Wilde small but meaningful allowances: access to 
                            books; permission to resume reading and writing; and, most importantly, the 
                            opportunity to revise earlier portions of his manuscript. 
                            This gesture made possible the composition of 
                            <title type="work" rend="italic">De Profundis</title>, Wilde’s long 
                            epistolary meditation written in Reading Gaol.
                            After Wilde’s release, Nelson received presentation copies of 
                            <title type="work" rend="italic">The Ballad of Reading Gaol</title> 
                            (1898) and 
                            <title type="work" rend="italic">The Importance of Being Earnest</title> 
                            (1899), attesting to Wilde’s personal gratitude. 
                            Nelson’s legacy survives primarily through Wilde’s testimony, and he is 
                            recognised by modern Wildean scholarship as a rare figure of empathy within 
                            the Victorian penal system.
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    
                    <person xml:id="pers_ross">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Robert</forename>
                            <addName type="middleName">Baldwin</addName>
                            <surname>Ross</surname>
                            <addName type="alias">Robbie Ross</addName>
                        </persName>
                        
                        <idno type="wikidata">Q1391982</idno>
                        
                        <state type="occupation">
                            <p>Journalist, art critic, gallery director, and literary executor of Oscar Wilde.</p>
                        </state>
                                                                        
                        <state type="relationship">
                            <p>Close friend, long-term confidant, and later literary executor of Oscar Wilde.</p>
                        </state>
                        
                        <note>
                            Robert Baldwin “Robbie” Ross (1869–1918) was a Canadian-born British journalist, critic, and one of the most significant figures in the preservation of Oscar Wilde’s literary legacy. 
                            A loyal friend from the 1880s until Wilde’s death, Ross defended him publicly during moments of intense scandal, provided emotional and financial support after Wilde’s release 
                            from prison, and encouraged him to continue writing during his exile. 
                            After Wilde’s death in 1900, Ross assumed the role of literary executor and played a decisive role in editing, republishing, and safeguarding Wilde’s manuscripts and 
                            correspondence. His efforts not only contributed to Wilde’s posthumous reputation but also ensured that many of Wilde’s works survived intact. 
                            Ross was a central figure in London’s artistic and literary circles, notably through his involvement with The Carfax Gallery, which he co-founded. 
                            Remembered for his integrity, devotion, and influence on the dissemination of Wilde’s œuvre, Ross remains an essential figure in Wildean scholarship.
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
                                  
            <settingDesc>
                <listPlace>
                    
                    <place xml:id="place_berneval">
                        <placeName type="official">Berneval-sur-Mer</placeName>
                        <placeName type="variant">Berneval</placeName>
                        <placeName type="current">Petit-Caux</placeName>
                        
                        <idno type="wikidata">Q21979907</idno>
                                                
                        <note>
                            Berneval-sur-Mer is a former coastal commune in the Seine-Maritime 
                            département (Normandy, France), today part of the commune of 
                            <placeName>Petit-Caux</placeName>. It was a quiet seaside village 
                            frequented by artists and writers in the nineteenth century.
                            
                            After his release from <placeName ref="#place_reading_gaol">Reading Gaol</placeName> 
                            in May 1897, Oscar Wilde stayed in Berneval-sur-Mer under the pseudonym 
                            <persName ref="#pers_wilde">Sebastian Melmoth</persName>. He lodged at the 
                            “Hôtel de la Plage,” where he attempted to resume writing and rebuild his 
                            life in relative anonymity. 
                            
                            Wilde remained in Berneval from late May until September 1897, 
                            when he left France temporarily and travelled to Naples, where he lived 
                            for several weeks with Lord Alfred Douglas before returning again to France. 
                            
                            The letter edited in this TEI file was written from Berneval during this 
                            period of fragile recovery.
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                    <place xml:id="place_reading_gaol">
                        <placeName type="official">HM Prison Reading</placeName>
                        <placeName type="common">Reading Gaol</placeName>
                        
                        <idno type="wikidata">Q3930959</idno>
                                                
                        <note>
                            Reading Gaol (HM Prison Reading) is a Victorian prison located in Reading, 
                            Berkshire, United Kingdom (Forbury Road). The prison was built in 1844 on the 
                            model of the “separate system”, intended to enforce isolation and penitential 
                            reflection. It is most famously associated with Oscar Wilde, who was 
                            incarcerated there from 1895 to 1897 under the Criminal Law Amendment Act. 
                            Wilde described the harsh conditions of the establishment in several writings, 
                            and his experience there gave rise to 
                            <title type="work" rend="italic">The Ballad of Reading Gaol</title> (1898), 
                            one of his major late works.
                        </note>
                    </place>
                    
                </listPlace>
            </settingDesc>
            
                       
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="#pers_wilde">Oscar Wilde</persName>
                    <placeName ref="#place_berneval">Berneval-sur-Mer</placeName>
                    <date when="1897-05-28">28 May 1897</date>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="#pers_nelson">Major J.O. Nelson</persName>
                    <note>Governor of Reading Gaol.</note>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc> <!-- Record of changes, revisions, and updates made to the TEI file over time. -->
            <change when="2025-11-16">
                <name>Clara Martin</name>
                <desc>Initial TEI encoding of the Wilde–Nelson letter.</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="letter" xml:id="nelson-letter">
                
                <!-- Name used after release + address block at the head of the letter -->
                <note type="letterhead">
                    <p>
                        My name is here,<lb/>
                        <persName type="pseudonym">
                            <hi rend="underline">
                                <choice>
                                    <abbr>Mons.</abbr>
                                    <expan>Monsieur</expan>
                                </choice>
                                Sebastian Melmoth
                            </hi>
                        </persName><lb/><lb/>
                        Hotel de la Plage<lb/>
                        <placeName ref="#place_berneval">Berneval-sur-Mer</placeName>.<lb/>
                        Près de <placeName>Dieppe</placeName>
                    </p>
                </note>
                
                <!-- Opening of the letter -->
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear <persName ref="#pers_nelson">Major Nelson</persName>,</salute>
                </opener>
                
                <!-- Paragraph 1 -->
                <p rend="indentation">
                    I had of course<lb/>
                    intended to write to you as<lb/>
                    soon as I had safely reached<lb/>
                    French soil, to express, however<lb/>
                    inadequately, my real feelings<lb/>
                    of what you must let me<lb/>
                    term, not merely sincere, but<lb/>
                    <hi rend="underline">affectionate</hi> gratitude to you<lb/>
                    for your kindness and gentleness<lb/>
                    to me in <placeName ref="#place_reading_gaol">prison</placeName>, and for the real<lb/>
                    care that you took of me<lb/>
                    at the end, when I was mentally<lb/>
                    upset and in a state of very<lb/>
                    terrible nervous excitement. You<lb/>
                    must not mind my using the<lb/>
                    word ‘gratitude.’ I used to<lb/>
                    think gratitude a burden to<lb/>
                    carry. Now I know that it is<lb/>
                    something that makes the heart<lb/>
                    lighter. The ungrateful man<lb/>
                    is one who walks slowly with<lb/>
                    feet and heart of lead. But<lb/>
                    when one knows the strange<lb/>
                    joy of gratitude to God and<lb/>
                    man the earth becomes lovelier<lb/>
                    to one, and it is a pleasure<lb/>
                    to count up, not one’s wealth<lb/>
                    but one’s debts, not the little<lb/>
                    that one possesses, but the<lb/>
                    much that one owes.
                </p>
                
                <!-- Paragraph 2 -->
                <p rend="indentation">
                    I abstained from writing,<lb/>
                    however, because I was haunted by<lb/>
                    the memory of the little<lb/>
                    children, &amp; the wretched<lb/>
                    half witted lad who was flogged<lb/>
                    by the Doctor’s orders. I could<lb/>
                    not have kept them out of<lb/>
                    my letter, and to have mentioned<lb/>
                    them to you might have put <hi rend="underline">you</hi><lb/>
                    in a difficult position. In your<lb/>
                    reply you <hi rend="underline">might</hi> have expressed<lb/>
                    sympathy with my views <pc>—</pc> I<lb/>
                    think you would have <pc>—</pc> and then<lb/>
                    on the appearance of my public<lb/>
                    letter you might have felt as<lb/>
                    I had, in some almost<lb/>
                    ungenerous or thoughtless<lb/>
                    way, procured your private<lb/>
                    opinion on official things, for<lb/>
                    use as corroboration.
                </p>
                
                <!-- Paragraph 3 -->
                <p rend="indentation">
                    I longed to speak to you<lb/>
                    about these things on the<lb/>
                    evening of my departure, but I<lb/>
                    felt that in my position as a<lb/>
                    prisoner it would have been<lb/>
                    wrong of me to do so, and that<lb/>
                    it would, or might have put<lb/>
                    you in a difficult position<lb/>
                    afterwards, as well as at the<lb/>
                    time. I only hear of my<lb/>
                    letter being published by a<lb/>
                    telegram from <persName ref="#pers_ross">Mr. Ross</persName>, but<lb/>
                    I hope they have printed it in<lb/>
                    full, as I tried to express<lb/>
                    in it my appreciation and<lb/>
                    admiration of your own humane<lb/>
                    spirit and affectionate interest<lb/>
                    in <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the prisoners under<lb/>
                    your charge. I did not wish<lb/>
                    people to think that any<lb/>
                    exception had been specially<lb/>
                    made for me. Such exceptional<lb/>
                    treatment as I received was by<lb/>
                    order of the Commissioners. You<lb/>
                    gave me the same kindness as<lb/>
                    you gave to everyone. Of course<lb/>
                    I made more demands, but<lb/>
                    then I think I had really more<lb/>
                    needs than others <pc>—</pc> and I lacked<lb/>
                    often their cheerful acquiescence <pc>—</pc>
                </p>
                
                <!-- Paragraph 4 -->
                <p rend="indentation">
                    Of course I side with<lb/>
                    the prisoners <pc>—</pc> I was one, and<lb/>
                    I belong to their class now <pc>—</pc><lb/>
                    I am not a scrap ashamed of<lb/>
                    having been in <placeName ref="#place_reading_gaol">prison</placeName>. I am<lb/>
                    horribly ashamed of the materialism<lb/>
                    of the life that brought me<lb/>
                    there. It was quite unworthy of an<lb/>
                    artist.
                </p>
                
                <!-- Paragraph 5 -->
                <p rend="indentation">
                    Of <ref target="#bibl_warder_martin">Martin</ref>, and the subjects<lb/>
                    of my letter I of course say<lb/>
                    nothing at all, except that<lb/>
                    the man who could change the<lb/>
                    system <pc>—</pc> if any one man can<lb/>
                    do so <pc>—</pc> is yourself. At present<lb/>
                    I write to ask you to allow<lb/>
                    me to sign myself, once at any<lb/>
                    rate in life,
                </p>
                
                <closer>
                    <salute>your sincere and grateful friend,</salute>
                    <signed><persName ref="#pers_wilde">Oscar Wilde</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>